Studying to become a lawyer
(Questioner) I am a college
student in my 20s.
(Questioner) As a college student,
I am charting my life's direction
with social and personal goals in mind.
I think it's important that
whatever choice we make,
we need to understand the reason for it,
And I think it's important to
live a fulfilling life.
(Questioner) I have read
many books on this subject.
(Questioner) But I have not found
many clear answers.
(Questioner) They all say vaguely to
examine yourself, etc.
I want to know what I can do specifically
to find the real meaning of life.
(Sunim) Okay.
(Sunim) How old are you?
(Questioner) I am 27 years old.
(Sunim) Do you study full-time? Or do
you work too?
I don't have a job right now.
I'm on leave from school.
I am preparing for an exam.
But because I don't really understand
why I need to take that exam,
I get easily distracted
when I'm trying to study.
That's my problem.
Are your really studying for the exam?
I studied hard in the beginning,
but nowadays, I am so distracted.
(Questioner) I've been reading
a lot of unrelated books.
So you're not working hard,
but you do study for the exam?
Yes, I do.
(Sunim) Do you have a goal?
(Sunim) Or have you given up?
I do have a goal.
What kind of exam are you preparing for?
(Questioner) I'm studying for
the exam to be a patent lawyer.
Why do you want to be a patent lawyer?
I attended some lectures
on patent lawyers,
and I thought it offers good
prospects for the future.
So I started to pursue it
without clear motivation.
I did study law with some interest,
But I felt conflicted when
I was studying science.
More importantly, I began
to wonder that maybe
I don't have clear
directions for this process.
As human beings, no matter what sort of
work we do, we need to eat first, right?
Yes, it's important to eat.
Clothing, too, right?
What?
(Sunim) We need clothing, too, right?
Yes.
(Sunim) Sleep?
So, first of all, we need the essentials:
food, clothing, and shelter.
Do these things just fall from the sky
or do we get them ourselves?
We take care of them.
(Sunim) We do, don't we?
So the very first thing to
do is to make a living.
No matter what you do,
whether as a Buddhist practitioner,
a social activist, or any other work,
What do we need to do first?
We need to make a living.
(Sunim) We need to earn a living
for ourselves. (Audience Laughter)
Under the age of 20, we can
depend on our parents.
It is the parents' responsibility to
provide for us when we are young.
But after the age of 20, parents are no
longer responsible for their children.
Whether you can eat or not, no matter what
work you do, who's responsible for you?
I am.
That's how we become adults.
Being an adult means that
we take responsibility
for our words, our action,
and our survival.
You can no longer depend on
anyone else for your own well-being.
No matter what you choose to do,
when you reach the age of 20,
You need to be physically
and mentally independent.
That is the most important thing.
Without being self-sufficient, you can't
do anything for more than a few days.
Even if you become a Buddhist monk,
you will not be able to continue for long.
How did people in Buddha's
time solve this problem?
They just decided not to concern
themselves with these basic needs.
They didn't eat, they didn't sleep.
That is one way of
dealing with these issues.
What does it mean to be not eating?
They didn't do anything to obtain food.
They only ate what others discarded.
If they received food from someone
else, they ate. If not, they didn't.
They did not beg for food.
By begging, they would be beggar.
Buddhist practitioners
must not become beggars.
For clothing, they just picked up
and wore what others discarded.
In those days, clothes were precious.
So nobody discarded clothes.
In India, people used cloth to cover
corpses, instead of coffins.
And people thought those shrouds
were tainted. Nobody touched them.
They didn't even use them as rags.
But the practitioners would
pick them up and wear them.
They slept in caves or under the trees.
They didn't need to worry about
the basic needs of food,
clothing, and shelter, did they?
They didn't need to.
That's how they solved those problems.
That's how spiritual practitioners
dealt with those problems.
Anyone can do that. Everyone here has
the option to do that. (Audience Laughter)
Don't we find a lot of food waste in
trash bins around town these days?
There's a lot of discarded food.
We can just pick that up and eat it.
You can also find discarded clothes
in the trash. We can wear that.
We can just sleep in the metro stations,
in underground tunnels, etc.
If we choose to live this way, we don't
have to make any effort to make a living.
That is a self-sufficient,
adult way of living.
We shouldn't think of this as
being homeless or beggars.
Beggars are beggars because they beg.
If you don't ask or beg,
you're not a beggar.
That's just your way of survival.
That is also the way of
animals for surviving.
That is how spiritual practitioners in
Buddha's time solved the basic needs of life.
We shouldn't think they didn't
take care of their basic needs.
They took care of them in their way.
So they didn't have to
worry about them at all.
After taking care of their needs
in their own way, what did they do?
They decided to do the work
of spiritual practice.
In those circumstances,
one must not marry or have children.
That would be irresponsible.
That is why Buddhist monks do not marry.
What about the people in ordinary lives?
The laypeople must make a living.
Farming, trading, or whatever else.
They all need to make a living.
That is why laypeople
must not beg for food.
(Sunim) If they do, they become beggars.
So, if I were to live as an independent
man, I need to make a living.
Before anything else,
we need to earn a living.
We can be students,
athletes, or whatever.
But before all else, who is
responsible for your basic needs?
You are.
You need to work even as day laborer.
Do whatever it takes to survive.
As you're providing for yourself,
what else can you do?
While earning a living, you can study law
and prepare for the bar exam.
Or you can study to
become a civil servant.
You can study whatever you want to
study as you make a living for yourself.
That is how you can truly study.
Then, you can ask yourself: if I'm busy
making a living, do I really have to study?
You'll start asking yourself that.
If you don't want to,
then you don't have to.
But if you still want to study to become
something else, you can decide.
For instance, monks who took care
of themselves in the minimalistic way,
did they do anything
else other than surviving?
If they did nothing else, they couldn't
be considered true practitioners.
They studied and observed their minds
after taking care of their basic needs.
They practiced to liberate themselves
from their own limitations.
Therefore, they were able
to give advice to laypeople.
They could help others with
emotional or mental difficulties.
Even if they owned nothing,
they could give help to others.
Practitioners do not receive
help. They give help.
They do not give material things,
but give spiritual comfort.
When you become an adult, you must
be able to contribute something to others.
Whether emotionally or materially.
You can make money and
support other people monetarily,
Or you can become an
attorney and help others in need.
You can do good work
with this basic foundation.
Without this, you cannot succeed.
You're most likely to give up
if you can't feed yourself.
Why? Because you can't
endure the difficulties.
(Sunim) But if you take care of yourself
and study for exams at the same time,
(Sunim) you can't help but study with
strong focus and determination.
(Sunim) You can accomplish a lot
even in a short period of time.
But many of us do not live this way.
We all need to be independent.
If you want to start a business
but don't have the capital for it,
Do we have to accumulate
enough capital only by hard labor?
Or can we persuade others to invest
in the business with your idea?
We can repay the investors
after we make some profit, right?
We can pay back the loan.
This is not about getting a free lunch.
Because I'm borrowing the
capital now to pay it back later.
The best way is the first option--
making a living through labor.
But there are other things you can do.
Instead, you can look for
investors, show them your idea,
And ask them how long they
can lend you the money for.
You borrow first and pay back later.
Who among the people you know
would be the most likely investors?
Your parents, right?
So you can tell your parents about
your plan in a sincere manner.
Say, "I have made such and such
plan, and it takes 2 or 3 years of
study for this much money."
"Can you lend me that money?"
"Since I have no income, I would very
much appreciate a low interest rate
or no interest at all." You need to
negotiate like this with your parents.
Since you're living in debt, you'll be
motivated to focus on your study.
But right now, you're not paying
for yourself, so you can take it easy.
You see no reason to work hard.
That is why being self-sufficient is a
the first requirement for adult life.
But within self-sufficiency,
there is true independence
and a degree of independence
with the help of others.
Even if you do receive help
from your parents for now,
You need to try to become fully independent
soon and be grateful for their help.
If not, you will not appreciate
any acts of generosity.
If you ask for money from other
people, do they just lend you money?
(Questioner) No, they don't.
Because you have no credit with them,
they won't lend you any money, right?
But your parents would.
They help you pursue your goals
because you're their child.
When you become successful later,
you must pay them back.
There is a third way. This, too, is built
on the principle of self-sufficiency.
You could say, for example, "I think the
unification of Korea is very important."
"I want to contribute to this cause."
"But I won't make any money
doing that. I have to pay for myself."
"Can you support me while I do this work?"
You could ask your parents, for example.
If your parents agree that this
is an important cause,
you can discuss that option with them.
You can say, "I would
like to do this work for a few years."
"Could you support me
while I'm doing that?"
Seeking support for this sort of
work is not for any private interest.
You're working for a common good, so it's
acceptable to get support from others.
"I want to help orphaned children. Can
you help me in this endeavor?" for example.
If you propose to do projects like this,
wouldn't there be some people
who want to help out? There would be.
This is the same thing.
Because the purpose of your work is to
help many people instead of yourself only,
You can ask for support from other people.
(Sunim) These are all appropriate
endeavors for independent adults.
(Sunim) Do you understand what I mean?
(Sunim) A way of life that is fit for a
fully self-sufficient, independent adult.
If you take responsibility
for your own life,
You can be happy and
joyful doing no matter what.
But the slight problem
in your case right now is that
You're not sure about
your own goals in life.
(Sunim) Although you're an adult,
you still depend on your parents.
(Sunim) You're living the life of
a parasite at your parents' expense.
(Sunim) You must give that up
and live on your own as an adult.
But if you were to do social
work or spiritual practice,
Asking for help from your parents
is not necessarily stealing from them.
Why not? Because you are asking
for their donation to a good cause.
Do you understand? In that case,
you're not asking as a child.
You're rather asking your parents as
a member of the bigger community to
help other people. During the period
of Korean independence movement,
didn't those activists gather support
from everyone, including their families?
They did.
Some even sold their families'
land to support the cause.
Therefore, if you're sure
of your own goals and aims,
There is no time for
you to waste right now.
(Questioner) Yes. You're right.
(Sunim Laughter) (Audience Laughter)
If you've decided you want to study law,
Tell your parents about your specific
plans and deadlines and ask for help.
Set a deadline for your loans from your
parents--1 year or 2 years--and write an IOU
How can you waste any time
if you're working with that deadline?
Imagine, if you received a
scholarship from a school,
Wouldn't you lose that funding if you
never study hard to earn that?
(Questioner) I'd lose it.
You'd lose it right away.
So stop thinking that you can
make excuses for yourself
because you're relying on your parents.
(Sunim) If you're past age 20, you need
to take responsibility for yourself.
(Sunim) You must live with that principle.
Thank you!
(Sunim Laughter) (Applause)